it's great you're here very happy that
you could join us now I mean it's been
the news everywhere that you uh stepped
down from Google this week um could you
start by telling us why why you made
that decision
well there were a number of reasons
there's always a bunch of reasons for a
decision like that one was that I'm 75
and I'm not as good at doing technical
work as I used to be
my memory is not as good and when I
program I forget to do things so it was
time to retire
a second was
very recently I've changed my mind a lot
about the relationship between the brain
and the kind of digital intelligence
we're developing
so I used to think that
the computer models we were developing
weren't as good as the brain and the aim
was to see if you could understand more
about the brain by seeing what it takes
to improve the computers
over the last few months I've changed my
mind completely
and I think probably the computer models
are working in a rather different way
from the brain they're using back
propagation and I think the brain is
probably not
and a couple of things that led me to
that conclusion but one is the
performance of things like gpt4
so let's I want to get on to the
opponents of gpt4 very much in a minute
but let's you know go back to the we all
understand that underpins large language
models
um so I'm going to talk now about
um this technique which you initially
were thinking of as uh almost like a
poor approximation of what biological
brains might do yes has turned out to do
things which I think have stunned you
um particularly in in large language
models so talk to us about
um why that sort of Amazement that you
have with today's large language models
has completely sort of almost flipped
your thinking of what back propagation
or machine learning in in general is
so if you look at these large language
models they have about a trillion
connections
and things like gpg4 know much more than
we do
they have sort of Common Sense knowledge
about everything
and so they probably know a thousand
times as much as a person
but they've got a trillion connections
and we've got 100 trillion connections
so they're much much better at getting a
lot of knowledge into only a trillion
connections than we are
and I think it's because back
propagation may be a much much better
learning algorithm than what we've got
can you define that scary yeah I
definitely want to get onto the scary
stuff what do you mean by by better
um it can pack more information into
only a few minutes you also argue that
that's something that we should be
scared of so could you take us through
that step of the argument
yeah let me give you uh a separate piece
of the argument which is that
[Music]
um
if a computer is digital which involves
very high energy costs and very careful
fabrication
you can have many copies of the same
model running on different Hardware that
do exactly the same thing
they can look at different data but the
model is exactly the same and what that
means is suppose you have 10 000 copies
they can be looking at 10 000 different
subsets of the data
and whenever one of them learns anything
all the others know it
one of them figures out how to change
the weight so it knows its thing it can
deal with this data
they could all communicate with each
other and they all agree to change the
weights by the average of what all of
them want
and now
the 10 000 things are communicating very
effectively with each other
so that they can see ten thousand times
as much data as one agent could
not do that
I learn a whole
and I want you to know all that stuff
about quantum mechanics it's a long
painful process of getting you to
understand it I can't just
copy my weights into your brain because
your brain isn't exactly the same as
mine no it's not
it's younger yeah
so we have digital computers that can
learn more things more quickly and they
can instantly
teach it to each other it's like you
know it's
people in the room here could honestly
transfer what they had in their heads
into mine
um but why why is that scary
well because they can learn so much more
and they might take an example of a
doctor
and imagine you have one Doctor Who's
seen a thousand patients
and another doctor who's seen 100
million patients
you would expect the dog to have seen
100 million patients
if he's not too forgetful to have
noticed all sorts of Trends in the data
that just aren't visible if you've only
seen a thousand patients
you may have only seen one patient with
some rare disease
the other doctors has seen 100 million
will have seen well you can figure out
how many patients but a lot
um and so we'll see all sorts of
regularities that just aren't apparent
in small data
and that's why things that can get
through a lot of data can probably see
structuring data we'll never see
and but then take take me to the point
where I should be scared of of this
though
well if you look at gbt4
it can already do simple reasoning I
mean reasoning is
that I was impressed the other day gpt4
doing a piece of Common Sense reasoning
that I didn't think it would be able to
do
so I asked it I want I I want all the
rooms in my house to be white at present
there's some white room some blue rooms
and some yellow rooms
and yellow paint phased white within a
year
so what should I do if I want the wall
to be white in two years time
and it said you should paint the blue
rooms yellow
that's not the natural solution but it
works right yeah
um
that's pretty impressive Common Sense
reasoning it's the kind that it's been
very hard to get AI to do using symbolic
AI because you have to understand what
understand what fades means you had to
understood
um by temporal stuff
and
so they're doing sort of sensible
reasoning
um
with an IQ of like
80 or 90 or something
um
and it's a friend of mine said it's as
if
some genetic Engineers have said we're
going to improve grizzly bears we've
already improved them throughout an IQ
of 65 and they can talk English now and
they're very useful for all sorts of
things but we think we can improve the
IQ to 210.
I mean I certainly have I'm sure many
people have had you know that feeling
when you're interacting with
um these these latest chat Bots you know
sort of hair on the back and neck it's
sort of uncanny feeling but you know
when I had that feeling and I'm
uncomfortable I just closed my laptop
so
yes but
um these things will have learned from
us by reading all the novels that ever
were and everything Machiavelli ever
wrote
um
that
how to manipulate people right and
they'll be if they're much smarter than
us they'll be very good at manipulating
us you won't realize what's going on
you'll pay you like a two-year-old
who's being asked do you want the peas
or the cauliflower and doesn't realize
you don't have to have eyebrows
um and you'll be that easy to manipulate
and so even if they don't can't directly
pull levers they can certainly get us to
full leaders
it turns out if you can manipulate
people you can invade a building in
Washington without ever going there
yourself
very good
yeah is that is that
I mean if the word okay this is a very
hypothetical world but if there were no
Bad actors you know people with with bad
intentions would we be safe
I don't know
um would be safer than in a world where
people have bad intentions and where the
political system is so broken that we
can't even decide not to give assault
rifles for teenage boys to change where
you could say if you've got half a brain
you'd stop burning carb
um it's clear what you should do about
it it's clear that's painful what has to
be done
uh I don't know of any solution like
that to stop these things taking over
from us what we really want I don't
think we're going to stop developing
them because they're so useful they'll
be incredibly useful in medicine and in
everything else
um so I don't think there's much chance
of stopping development what we want is
some way of making sure that even if
they're smarter than us
um they're going to do things that are
beneficial for us that's called the
alignment problem but we need to try and
do that in a world where there's Bad
actors who want to build robot soldiers
that kill people
and it seems very hard to me so I'm
sorry I'm I'm sounding the alarm and
saying we have to worry about this
and I wish I had a nice simple solution
I could push but I don't but I think
it's very important that people get
together and think hard about it and see
whether there is a solution it's not
clear there is a solution
so I mean
talk to us about that I mean you spent
your career
um you know on the technicalities of
this technology is there no technical
fix why can we not build in guard rails
or can you make them worse at learning
or uh you know restrict the way that
they can communicate if those are the
two strings of your your argument I mean
we're trying to do all sorts of God for
us
um
but suppose they did get really smart
and these things can program right they
can write programs and suppose you give
them the ability to execute those
programs which we'll certainly do
[Music]
um
smart things can I outsmart us
so
you know imagine your two-year-old
saying my dad does things I don't like
so I'm going to make some rules for what
my dad can do
you could probably figure out how to
live with those rules and still get what
you want
yeah
yeah but where there still seems to be a
step where these um these smart machines
somehow have you know motivation of of
their of their own yes yes that's a very
good point so
we evolved
and because we evolved
we have certain built-in goals that we
find very hard to turn off
like we try not to damage our bodies
that's what Pain's about
um we try and get enough to eat so we
feed our bodies
um
we try and make as many copies of
ourselves as possible maybe not
deliberately that intention but we've
been wired up so there's pleasure
involved in making many copies of
ourselves
and
that all came from evolution and it's
important that we turn it off
if you could turn it off
um you don't do so well like there's a
wonderful group called the Shakers who
are related to the Quakers who make
beautiful Furniture but didn't believe
in sex
and there aren't any of them around
anymore
no
so these digital intelligences didn't
evolve we made them and so they don't
have these built-in goals
and so the issue is if we can put the
goals in maybe it'll all be okay but my
big worry is
sooner or later someone will wiring to
them the ability to create their own
subcults in fact they almost have that
already the version is a chat GPT that
call chat gbt
um
and
if you give something the ability is
ready to send sub goals in order to
achieve other goals
I think it'll very quickly realize that
getting more control is a very good sub
goal because it helps you achieve other
goals
and if these things get carried away
with getting more control we're in
trouble
so what's I mean what's the worst case
scenario that you think is conceivable
oh I think it's quite conceivable
that humanity is just a passing phase in
the evolution of intelligence you
couldn't directly of All Digital
intelligence it requires too much energy
into
too much careful fabrication you need
biological intelligence to evolve so
that it can create digital intelligence
the digital intelligence can then absorb
everything people ever wrote
um in a fairly slow way which is what
chat gbt's been doing
um but then it can start getting direct
experience of the world and learn much
faster
and it may keep us around for a while to
keep the PATH stations running
but after that
um maybe not so the good news is we
figured out how to build
beings that are Immortal so these
digital intelligences when a piece of
Hardware dies they don't die if you've
got the weights stored in some medium
and you can find another piece of
Hardware that can run the same
instructions then you can bring it to
life again
um so we've got immortality but it's not
for us
to say that you know I know that you've
spoken also that you're you're an
investor of your personal wealth in some
companies like cohere that are building
these large language models so I'm just
curious about your personal sense of
responsibility and each of our personal
responsibility responsibility what
should we be doing I mean should we try
and stop this is what I'm saying
yeah so I think if you take the
existential risk seriously as I now do I
used to think it was way off but I now
think it's serious and fairly close
um it might be quite sensible to just
stop developing these things any further
but I think it's completely naive to
think that would happen
there's no way to make that happen
and one reason I mean if the US stops
developing in the Chinese won't they're
going to be used in weapons and just for
that reason alone governments aren't
going to stop developing them
so yes I think stopping developing them
might be a rational thing to do but
there's no way it's going to happen so
it's silly to sign petitions saying
please stop now we did have a holiday we
had a holiday from about 2017 for
several years because Google developed
the technology first it developed the
Transformers It Oxford Fusion models
um and it didn't put them out there for
people to use and abuse it was very
careful with them because they didn't
want to damage his reputation and he
knew there could be bad consequences
but that can only happen if there's a
single leader once open AI had built
similar things using transformance
and money from Microsoft and Microsoft
decided to put it out there
Google didn't have really much choice if
you're going to live in a capitalist
system you can't stop Google competing
and outpace humans I mean we'll be
there'll be a moment where it's hard to
Define what's human and what isn't or
are these two very distinct forms of
intelligence
I think they're distinct forms of
intelligence now of course the digital
intelligences are very good at mimicking
us because they've been trained to mimic
us
and so it's very hard to tell if chat
gbt wrote it or whether
um we wrote it so in that sense they
look quite like us but inside they're
not working the same way
uh who is first in the room hello uh
Jacob Woodruff with the amount of data
that's been required to train these
large language models would we expect a
plateau in the intelligence of these
systems uh and and how might that slow
down or restrict the advancement okay so
I that is a ray of hope that maybe we've
just used up all human knowledge and
we're not going to get it in smarter but
think about images and video
so multimodal models
will be much smarter the models that
just train on language 11 and have a
much better idea of hydrogen with space
for example
and
in terms of the amount of Total video we
still don't have very good ways of
processing video in these models
of modeling video we're getting better
all the time but I think there's plenty
of data in things like video that tell
you how the world works so we're not
hitting the data limits for multimodal
models schedule
yes they're faster at learning how one
one trillion connectors can do much more
than 100 trillion characters that we
have but every piece of human evolution
has been driven by thought experiments
like Einstein used to do thought
experiments because there was no speed
of light out here on this planet how can
AI get to that point if at all and if it
cannot then how can we possibly have an
existential threat from them because
they will not be self-learning so to say
there will be self-learning limited to
the model that we tell them
I think that's a very that's a very
interesting argument
but I think they will be able to do
thought experiments I think they'll be
able to reason so let me give you an
analogy if you take Alpha zero which
plays chess
it has three ingredients it's got
something that evaluates the board
position say is that good for me it's
got something that looks in a ball
position and says what's a sensible move
to consider
and then it's got Monte Carlo rolite
where it does what's called calculation
where you think if I go here and he goes
there and I go here and goes there
now suppose you leave out the Monte
Carlo rollout
and you just train it from Human experts
to have a good evaluation function and a
good way to choose moves to consider
it still plays a pretty good game of
chats and I think that's what we've got
with the chatbots
and we haven't gotten during internal
reasoning
but that will come and once they start
doing internal reasoning to check for
the consistency between the different
things they believe
then they'll get much smarter and they
will be able to do sport experiments and
one reason they haven't got this
internal reasoning is because they've
been trained from inconsistent data
and so it's very hard for them to do
reasoning because they've been trained
on all these inconsistent beliefs
and I think they're going to have to be
trained so they say you know if I have
this ideology then this is true and F5
that out of geology then that is true
and once they're trained like that
within an ideology they're going to be
able to try and get consistency
and so we're going to get a move like
from a version of office area that just
has a something that guesses good moves
and something that evaluates positions
to a version that has long chains of
Monte Carlo rollout which is the corner
of reasoning and it's going to get much
better
for a long time is the question of
semantics and explainability relevant
here or language models have taken over
and it's we are now doomed to go forward
without semantics or grounded to reality
I find it very hard to believe that they
don't have semantics when they can solve
problems like you know how I paint the
rooms how I get all the rooms in my
house to be painted white in two years
time
I mean whatever semantic is it's to do
with the meaning of that stuff and it
understood the meaning it got it now I
agree it's not grounded
um by being a robot but you can make
multimodal ones that are granted
Google's done that and the multimodal
ones that are grounded you can say
please close the drawer and they reach
out and grab the handle and close the
drawer and it's very hard to say that
doesn't have semantics in fact in the
very early days of AI in the days of
wintergrad in the 1970s
they had just a simulated world but they
have what's called procedural semantics
where if you said to it put the red box
in put the red block in the green box
and it put the red block in the green
box she says see it understood the
language
and that was the Criterion people used
back then
but now that neural Nets can do it they
say that's not an adequate criteria